

Diego de Freitas Aranha

Associate Professor at Department of Computer Science, Aarhus University, Denmark

Åbogade 34, 8200 Aarhus N, Aarhus, Denmark.

E-mail: dfaranha@cs.au.dk Phone: +45 91 88 14 46

Website: https://sites.google.com/site/dfaranha

RESEARCH OBJECTIVES Enable the development of a new generation of secure computer systems through efficient and robust cryptography, privacy-preserving protocols and lessons from security analysis of real-world systems.

RESEARCH Interests Efficient algorithms and software implementations for symmetric and public key cryptography; privacy-preserving cryptographic protocols; security of real-world systems for banking infrastructure and electronic voting.

Public Profiles

- ResearcherID: https://www.researcherid.com/rid/J-9961-2012
- Google Scholar: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=FF26-mIAAAAJ
- SCOPUS: https://www.scopus.com/authid/detail.uri?authorId=16041624100
- DBLP: http://dblp.uni-trier.de/pers/hy/a/Aranha:Diego_F=

EDUCATION

University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Canada

Visiting PhD student

04/2010 - 04/2011

- Project: Pairing-Based Cryptography: Theory and Practice
- Advisor: Alfred Menezes
- Area of study: Cryptographic Engineering

University of Campinas, Campinas, Brazil

PhD in Computer Science

03/2007 - 08/2011

- Thesis: Efficient software implementation of curve-based cryptography
- Advisor: Julio López
- Area of study: Cryptographic Engineering

Master of Computer Science

03/2005 - 02/2007

- Dissertation: Name services and routing in anonymizing networks
- Advisor: Julio López
- Area of study: Computational anonymity

University of Brasília, Brasília, Brazil

Bachelor of Computer Science

02/2000 - 02/2005

- Project: An anonymizing transport layer with applications to censorship-resistant services
- Advisor: João Gondim
- Area of study: Computational anonymity

Professional Experience

Aarhus University, Aarhus, Denmark

 $Associate\ Professor,\ Department\ of\ Computer\ Science$

08/2020 - Present

- Researcher on Cryptographic Engineering and Systems Security.
- Lectured undergrad courses on Computer Architecture and grad courses on Systems Security.

Assistant Professor, Department of Engineering

07/2018 - 07/2020

- Researcher on Cryptographic Engineering and Network Security.
- Lectured undergrad courses on Data Structures and graduate courses on Network Security.

University of Campinas, Campinas, Brazil

Assistant Professor, Institute of Computing

02/2014 - 06/2018

- Researcher on Cryptographic Engineering and Systems Security.
- Lectured undergrad courses on Algorithms and Computer Programming, Computer Architecture, Assembly Programming, and Competitive Programming.
- Lectured graduate courses on Cryptography, Secure Programming and Algorithm Complexity.

University of Brasília, Brasília, Brazil

Assistant Professor, Department of Computer Science

11/2011 - 02/2014

- Researcher on PUF-based Cryptography and Electronic Voting.
- Lectured undergrad courses on Cryptography, Object-Oriented Programming, Computer Architecture, Competitive Programming, Computational Logic, Systems Software.

CertiVox/MIRACL, London, UK

Contractor/Developer

09/2010 - 11/2011

• Implemented encrypted messaging in C++ and JavaScript employing pairing-based cryptography.

Honors	AND
AWARDS	

• Supervisor of Best MSc. Dissertation defended in Brazil on Computer Architecture and	d High-
Performance Computing	2019
• Top 1% reviewers for cross-field research on Publons	2018
• Invited to discuss security issues with electronic voting at Brazilian Senate	2018
• Selected to defend strong encryption on public hearing at Brazilian Supreme Court	2017
• Google Research Awards in Latin America for research in privacy 2015	5/2016
• Innovators Under 35 Brazil, awarded by MIT TechReview for work in electronic voting	2015
• Raised US\$ 30,000 in crowdfunding campaign for YouInspect project	2014

Best Paper Award in CHES

• Best PhD dissertation in Brazil on Computer Security and Cryptography

• 2nd Best Computer Science PhD Thesis in Brazil, awarded by Brazilian Computer Society 2012

• Best PhD dissertation defended in 2011 at Institute of Computing, University of Campinas 2012 • Invited to discuss security issues with electronic voting at Brazilian Congress

• 1st place at the 2nd Edition of the Public Security Tests of the Electronic Voting System organized by the Brazilian Electoral Authority 2012

• Visiting PhD Student Scholarship by CAPES funding agency

2010-2011

• Prestigious PhD Scholarship by FAPESP funding agency

2007-2010

2013

2012

• 5th/8th place in South American ACM International Collegiate Programming Contest 2003/2004

QUANTITATIVE INDICATORS

Completed supervisions: 29 undergrad research and final projects, 5 MSc. dissertations, 4 MSc. co-supervisions, 2 PhD co-supervisions, 1 Postdoc.

Publications: 22 journal articles, 3 book chapters, 37 papers in conference proceedings, 7 papers in peer-reviewed workshops.

Citations: 2199 (Google Scholar), 1089 (ResearchGate), 777 (Scopus), 472 (ISI).

H-Index: 23 (Google Scholar), 18 (ResearchGate), 15 (Scopus), 15 (ISI).

Funding

Aarhus University, Aarhus, Denmark

RENAIS: Residue Number Systems for Cryptography (PI)

07/2021 - Present

- Grant: Independent Research Fund Denmark, DKK 2,871,000
- Objective: Develop algorithms for field arithmetic in RNS representation.

BAN – Blockchain Network Academy (PI)

01/2020 - Present

- Grant: Danish Industry Fund, DKK 1,673,000 for AU within total of 6,750,000 to consortium.
- Objective: Develop training materials and use cases for secure blockchain applications.

Verifiable cryptographic software (PI)

08/2019 - Present

- Grant: Partnership with Concordium Blockchain Research Center, DKK 2,250,000.
- Objective: Develop techniques for formal verification of cryptographic software.

Cybersecurity in secure manufacturing (PI)

12/2018 - 10/2020

- Grant: Partnership with Aerospace & Defence Manufacturing Groupe (ADMAG) in the Smart Industry program, DKK 1,000,000.
- Objective: Prototype and deploy techniques for secure sharing of production data.

University of Campinas, Campinas, Brazil

Privacy-preserving analytics with differential privacy (PI)

04/2018 - 04/2019

- Grant: Seed funding from LG Electronics, US\$ 50,000.
- Objective: Design efficient protocols and implementations satisfying differential privacy.

Efficient and secure cryptography for IoT (PI)

02/2015 - 03/2018

- Grant: Partnership with LG Electronics, US\$ 250,000.
- Objective: Design efficient software implementations for lightweight cryptography.

Machine learning over encrypted data using homomorphic encryption (PI) 10/2015 - 10/2017

- Grant: Google Research Awards for Latin America, US\$ 40,000.
- Objective: Design algorithms and protocols for machine learning tasks over encrypted data.

Secure execution of cryptographic algorithms (co-PI)

11/2015 - 12/2018

- Grant: Intel/FAPESP Research Partnership for Technological Innovation, US\$ 160,000.
- Objective: Design instruction set extensions for side-channel resistant cryptography.

University of Brasília, Brasília, Brazil

Physical Unclonable Functions for SoC Devices (co-PI)

07/2012 - 11/2015

- Grant: Partnership with Intel Labs, US\$ 87,000.
- Objective: Design energy-efficient constructions and protocols for PUF-based cryptography.

SELECTED INVITED AND CONTRIBUTED TALKS "Return of the insecure Brazilian voting machines". In DEF CON 26 Voting Village, USA, 2018; Black Hat Asia, Singapore, 2019; Workshop on E-lections, Israel, 2019; InfoSecurity Denmark, 2019.

"Security and privacy challenges in modern embedded systems". In *Grundfos Archimedes Lecture*, Denmark, 2019.

"Pairings are not dead, just resting", "Introduction to pairings". In 21st Workshop on Elliptic Curve Cryptography (ECC), Netherlands, 2017.

"Lightweight cryptography on ARM". In Software Performance Enhancement of Encryption and Decryption and Benchmarking (SPEED-B), Netherlands, 2016; and NIST Lightweight Cryptography Workshop (LWC), USA, 2016.

"Software vulnerabilities in the Brazilian voting machine". In 5th Real World Cryptography Conference (RWC), Stanford, USA, 2016.

"Security Analysis of the Brazilian voting machine", "Software implementation of pairings". In 3rd Advanced School on Cryptology and Information Security in Latin America (AS-Crypto), Mexico, 2015.

"Efficient binary field arithmetic and applications to curve-based cryptography". In 14th International Workshop on Cryptographic Hardware and Embedded Systems (CHES), Belgium, 2012; and Microsoft Research (MSR), USA, 2012.

"Software vulnerabilities in the Brazilian voting machine". In Electronic Voting Technology Workshop/Workshop on Trustworthy Elections (USENIX EVT/WOTE), USA, 2012.

"Software implementation of pairings". In The 15th Workshop on Elliptic Curve Cryptography (ECC), France, 2011.

PhD. And Postdoc Supervisions Benjamin Salling Hvaas, PhD student at Aarhus University (co-supervision)

Topic: Verifiable pairing-based cryptographic software 08/2019 - Present

Akira Takahashi, PhD student at Aarhus University (co-supervision)

Topic: Fault side-channel attacks on signature schemes 01/2019 - Present

Antônio Carlos Guimarães Junior, PhD student at University of Campinas (co-supervision)

Topic: Privacy-preserving computation in the cloud 07/2019 - Present

Rogério Vinicius Matos Rocha, PhD student at University of Campinas

Topic: Differential Privacy in automotive applications 03/2017 - Present

Pedro Geraldo Morelli Rodrigues Alves, PhD student at University of Campinas

Topic: GPU-accelerated homomorphic encryption 03/2016 - Present

Jheyne Nayara Ortiz, PhD student at University of Campinas (co-supervision)

Topic: Efficient parameters for lattice-based cryptography 03/2016 - Present

Amanda Cristina Davi Resende, PhD student at University of Campinas

Topic: Private Set Intersection protocols 03/2015 - Present

Narcise B. Mbiang, PhD student at University of Dschang, Cameroon (co-supervision)

Topic: Computing the Optimal Ate pairing at high security levels 03/2015 - Present

Caio Hoffman, PhD at University of Campinas (co-supervision)

Topic: Computer Security by Hardware-Intrinsic Authentication 09/2015 - 01/2019

Eduardo Moraes de Morais, PhD at University of Campinas (co-supervision)

Topic: CCA1-Secure Somewhat Homomorphic Encryption 04/2010 - 06/2016

Karina Mochetti de Magalhães, Postdoc at University of Campinas

Topic: Formal security analysis of PUF-based protocols 04/2015 - 11/2015

MSc. Supervisions

Joseph Alnajjar, MSc at Aarhus University (co-supervision)

Topic: Efficient implementation of new families of pairing-friendly curves 01/2019 - 07/2019

Antônio Carlos Guimarães Junior, MSc at University of Campinas

Topic: Secure and efficient implementation of code-based cryptography 03/2017 - 01/2019

Otávio Oliveira Napoli, MSc at University of Campinas (co-supervision)

Topic: Timing Side-Channel Analysis of Dynamic Binary Translators 03/2017 - 04/2019

Hayato Fujii, MSc at University of Campinas

Topic: Efficient Curve25519 Implementation for ARM Microcontrollers 03/2016 - 05/2018

Edson Floriano de Sousa Junior, MSc at University of Brasília (co-supervision)

Topic: Privacy in Shared-memory Tuple Spaces 03/2015 - 12/2017

Jheyne Nayara Ortiz, MSc at University of Campinas (co-supervision)

Topic: Efficient secure Gaussian sampling for lattice-based cryptography 03/2014 - 03/2016

Hilder Vitor Lima Pereira, MSc at University of Campinas

Topic: Machine learning over encrypted data 07/2014 - 09/2016

Pedro Geraldo Morelli Rodrigues Alves, MSc at University of Campinas

Topic: Computing over encrypted data using GPGPUs 07/2014 - 07/2016

Workshop Presentations

"High-speed parallel software implementation of the η_T pairing". In Software Performance Enhancement of Encryption and Decryption and Cryptographic Compilers (SPEED-CC), Germany, 2009.

"Efficient implementation of elliptic curves on sensor nodes", and "NanoPBC: Implementing Cryptographic Pairings on an 8-bit Platform". In Conference on Hyperelliptic curves, discrete Logarithms, Encryption, etc., Chile, 2009.

Professional Service

Program co-Chair of LATINCRYPT 2014 and SBSEG 2014 (Brazilian Symposium on Information and Computational Systems Security).

Co-founder and Program Co-Chair for two editions of the Workshop on Election Technology (WTE), the first academic workshop in Brazil for research on this topic.

Steering Committee member of the LATINCRYPT conference.

Program Committee member of SBSEG 2012-2017, PAIRING 2013, ICFCNA 2014, ISC 2016, ACNS 2017, WAIFI 2018/2020, LightSec 2018, KANGACRYPT 2018, IEEE CCNC 2017-2019, LATINCRYPT 2015/2017/2019, INDOCRYPT 2016/2018/2019, FC 2017-2020, CHES 2017-2019, PKC 2018-2019, SAC 2018-2019, IEEE Wireless Africa 2019.

Editoral Board member of IACR Transactions on Cryptographic Hardware and Embedded Systems (TCHES), Journal of Universal Computer Science (JUCS) and Cambridge Experimental Results (ER).

Reviewer for 46 academic journals, including Journal of Cryptographic Engineering, IEEE Transactions on Computers, IEEE Security and Privacy, IEEE Transactions on Circuits and Systems, IEEE Transactions on Dependable and Secure Computing, IEEE Transactions on VLSI, IEEE Transactions on Information Theory, ACM Transactions on Embedded Computing Systems, The Computer Journal, Designs, Codes and Cryptography, Journal of Cryptology; and 31 academic conferences, including PKC, CT-RSA, ASIACRYPT and CHES.

Reviewer for grant proposals submitted to the Israeli Ministry of Science, Technology and Space in Israel; the São Paulo Research Support Foundation (FAPESP) in Brazil; and Comisión Nacional de Investigación Científica y Tecnológica (CONACYCT) in Chile.

Membership

Principal Investigator at the Concordium Blockchain Research Center.

Work Package Leader in Cybersecurity at the DIGIT Centre for Digitalisation, Big Data and Data Analytics.

Member of the International Association for Cryptologic Research (IACR).

COMMUNITY OUTREACH

Co-founder and leader of YouInspect project (*Projeto Você Fiscal*) for voting machine (in)security awareness, election observation and crowdsourced verification of election results.

Software

Lead developer and founder of the RELIC cryptographic toolkit: http://github.com/relic-toolkit

TEACHING EXPERIENCE Teaching experience described in detail by the portfolio table presented below.

		-	E		1	-	A
rear	Title of course	Kole		Farticipants	Involvement		,
707	CIC 114/85 - Object-Oriented Fro-	Lecturer	instruction	o undergrads	from a collection	bac., ard	z written exams, I large
2012	CIC 117366 – Computational Logic	Lecturer	60-hour classrom	35 undergrads	Took over ongoing	BSc., 2nd	2 written exams
	•		Ē.)		ter	
2012	CIC 116785 – Architecture of Digital	Lecturer	60-hour classrom	Approx. 15 per	Planning and conduct-	BSc., 4th	2 written exams, seminar
			instruction	term	ŋg.	ster	
2013	CIC 115432 – System Software	Lecturer	60-hour classrom	19 in first term, 35	Materials, planning	BSc., 6th	2 written exams, 3 pro-
			instruction	l term	io	semester	gramming projects
2012–2013	CIC 116947 – Competitive Program-	1/3 Lecturer	30-hour classrom,	Approx. 15 per	Restructuring, plan-	BSc., all levels	Programming contests
0010	CIC 1104E0 Ell 1: 1	-	IS		CC		c
2012-2013	CIC 116458 – Theory of Encoding and	Lecturer	bu-hour classrom	5 in first term, 13	Restructuring, plan-	BSc., last year	2 written exams, 3 pro-
0010			Instruction	c	∃T		gramming projects
2012-2013	CIC 116475/116921 – Final Project	Supervisor	Supervised BSc. fi-	5 projects, 6 stu-	Weekly meetings for	BSc., last year	BSc. dissertation examina-
0100		-	힜	dents			uon
2012	CIC 310504 - Topics in Computing (Characteraphy)	Lecturer	bu-hour classrom	4 grad students	Creation, structuring,	MSc., nrst year	2 written exams and 3 pro-
2014-2016	MC030 - Undergraduate Final Project	Supervisor	Supervised ad-	6 students with in-	Weekly meetings for	BSc last year	BSc dissertation examina-
			dies :	dividual projects	i, including		tion
2014-2016	MC040/MC041 - Undergraduate Be-	Supervisor	Supervisor or un-	6 students with in-	Weekly meetings for	BSc., all levels	Manuscript examination
			(7)	dividual projects		(i)	
2014-2015	MC404 – Computer Organization and	Lecturer	30-hour class, 30-	Approx. 50 per	Materials, planning,	BSc., 4th	2 written exams, 8 pro-
	Assembly Programming		hour lab instruc-	term	teaching.	semester	gramming assignments
2015–2017	MC889/MO421 - Introduction to	Lecturer	60-hour class in-	Approx. 18 under-	Materials, planning,	All levels	2 written exams, 3 pro-
	Cryptography		struction	grads, 8 grad students per term	teaching.		gramming projects
2015	MC931/MO834 - Secure Programming and Malware Analysis	1/2 Lecturer	60-hour class in-	17 undergrad, 9	Materials, planning,	All levels	2 written exams, 5 pro-
9018 9018	MC109 Alminithme and Commentant		0000	1.	0		9 mitter cross 10 mg
2012–2010	MC102 - Algorithms and Computer Programming	Lecturer	60-nour class, 50- hour lab instruc- tion	Approx. 50 per term	Conducting a coordinated course.	bsc., 2nd semester	z written exams, 10 programming tasks
2016	MC621/MC821 - Competitive Pro-	1/2 Lecturer	15-hour class, 45-	Approx. 15 per	Lecturing classes.	BSc., senior	Programming contests
2016–2017	MC721/MC921 - Competitive Pro-	1/2 Lecturer	15-hour class, 45-	Approx. 15 per	Lecturing classes.	BSc., senior	Programming contests
	gramming Challenges II	1	hour lab	term			
2014	MO417 – Algorithm Complexity	Lecturer	60-hour class in-	27 grad students	Materials, planning,	MSc./PhD.,	3 written exams and 7
2019	Internet of Things Technology	Examiner	60-hour class in-	17 grad students	Internal co-examiner	MSc.	Oral examination
2019	Fundamentals of Computer Security	Lecturer	60-hour class in-	4 grad students	Materials, planning,	MSc., second	3 practical assignments
			struction			year	- 1
2020	Algorithms and Data Structures	Lecturer	60-hour class in- struction	25 undergrad students	Materials, planning, teaching.	BSc., second vear	7 Hand-ins and 1 written exam
2020	Network Security	Lecturer	60-hour class in-	50 grad students	Materials, planning,	MSc., senior	3 programming assign-
	•		η			,	ments and 1 final project
2021	Computer Architecture, Operating	Lecturer	60-hour class in-	100 undergrad stu-	Teaching half of the	BSc., senior	10 hand-ins and 1 written
	Systems and Inetworks		struction	dents	course		exam